<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Wishful Coding]]></title>
  <link href="http://wishfulcoding.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://wishfulcoding.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-08-22T01:28:15+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://wishfulcoding.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Leonardo]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Adding file size in bytes to Explorer.s Details View on Windows 2000 and XP]]></title>
    <link href="http://wishfulcoding.com/blog/2012/08/22/adding-file-size-in-bytes-to-explorer-dot-s-details-view-on-windows-2000-and-xp/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-22T01:19:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://wishfulcoding.com/blog/2012/08/22/adding-file-size-in-bytes-to-explorer-dot-s-details-view-on-windows-2000-and-xp</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Mi biggest pet peeve on Windows Explorer is that there is no way to show the size of a file in bytes without having to open the <a href="https://raw.github.com/dredix/FileSizeXP/master/doc/images/FileProperties.png">properties dialog box</a>. You would think the Details view is a great place for that, considering the remarkable selection of columns you can include. Seriously, there is a <em>Mood</em> column but no <em>Size in bytes</em> or equivalent?</p>

<p>On Windows XP and previous versions, you could write a <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/desktop/cc144067(v=vs.85">shell extension</a>.aspx) that implemented the <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/desktop/bb776147(v=vs.85">IColumnProvider</a>.aspx) interface and add custom columns as needed. <a href="http://tortoisesvn.net/docs/release/TortoiseSVN_en/tsvn-dug-wcstatus.html#id663427">TortoiseSVN</a> used these kind of extensions, for example, to show the status of files under source control directly on Windows Explorer.</p>

<p>On Windows Vista, however, Microsoft <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/desktop/bb776147(v=vs.85">decided to remove the IColumnProvider interface</a>.aspx):</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>Note</strong>  Support for <strong>IColumnProvider</strong> has been removed as of Windows Vista. The Windows property system is used in its place. See <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/desktop/ff728898(v=vs.85">Windows Property System</a>.aspx) for conceptual materials that explain the use of the new system.</p></blockquote>

<p>My guess is that rogue extensions were causing a lot of performance/stability issues on Windows Explorer and Microsoft didn&#8217;t like being blamed for them (&#8220;Why is Explorer so slow? Stupid Microsoft Die Die Die!&#8221;), so they decided to retire the interface altogether. I haven&#8217;t got too far into the Windows property system but I suspect you cannot mimic the full functionality of custom columns on the details view for every type of file.</p>

<p>Anyway, even if I came 11 years late to the party and it&#8217;s no longer relevant, I decided to take a shot at it and implemented a <a href="https://github.com/dredix/FileSizeXP">shell extension for showing the size of file in bytes</a>. No more <a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/b/oldnewthing/archive/2011/03/15/10140985.aspx">undesirable rounding up/down to kilobytes</a> for the benefit of ancient programs that have probably fallen into oblivion.</p>

<p>When installed, the extension adds a new column called <strong>Size in Bytes</strong> which can be added to the explorer&#8217;s Details View:</p>

<p><img src="http://wishfulcoding.com//raw.github.com/dredix/FileSizeXP/master/doc/images/ColumnSelection.png" alt="Column Selection" /></p>

<p>Select it, and you&#8217;ll get an extra column with the file size in glorious bytes:</p>

<p><a href="https://raw.github.com/dredix/FileSizeXP/master/doc/images/Explorer.png"><img alt="Details View" style="width: 100%" src="http://wishfulcoding.com//raw.github.com/dredix/FileSizeXP/master/doc/images/Explorer.png" /></a></p>

<p>If you still use Windows 2000 or XP <s>don&#8217;t you think is time to move on?</s> and want to use the extension, follow these steps:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Download the DLL: <a href="https://github.com/dredix/FileSizeXP/raw/master/bin/FileSizeXP.dll">FileSizeXP.dll</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>Put it wherever you want. C:\Utils is as good a place as any.</p></li>
<li><p>Register it by running the following command:<br/>
  <code>regsvr32 C:\path\to\file\FileSizeXP.dll</code></p></li>
<li><p>Restart the PC.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Note, however, the following caveats:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>The extension does not, I repeat, DOES NOT work on Windows Vista and newer versions. For that you will need need an Explorer replacement, like <a href="http://zabkat.com/">Zabkat&#8217;s Xplorer<sup>2</sup></a>, or just give up on showing full size in bytes in Explorer.</p></li>
<li><p>I haven&#8217;t actually tried the extension on Windows 2000.</p></li>
<li><p>Sorting files by the new column seems to be broken at the moment. I&#8217;ll go back and fix it, hopefully before Windows XP goes out of support.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>If you decided to trust a random guy on the Internet and try this extension, please do let me know how it went.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
